Register of the World War II pictorial collection
Hoover Institution Archives
World War II pictorial collection
1937-1945
XX222
Hoover Institution Archives
181 envelopes, 1 manuscript box, 1 oversize box, 3 album boxes, 2 slide boxes, 1 oversize folder (22.4 linear feet)
Photographs and postcards depicting a variety of scenes and personalities from World War II. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Access
The collection is open for research. Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items, computer media, and digital files. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos, films, or digital files during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Alternate Forms Available
Digital copies of select records also available at https://digitalcollections.hoover.org.
Scope and Content of Collection
Photographs and postcards depicting a variety of scenes and personalities from World War II.
Slides (Photography).; World War, 1939-1945--Pictorial works.
- Photographs and postcards depicting various scenes from World War II (Envelope A)
- 20 unidentified photographs of American soldiers in World War II, apparently taken in the Philippines (Envelope B)
- Photographs of German armed forces in Germany, Poland, Denmark, Norway, Russia and North Africa, and of the German home front, 1939-1943 (Envelope C-D)
- German army photographs depicting activities of the German army in North Africa, 1942-1943 (Envelope E-L)
  Scope and Contents note
  Copies from originals held by Michael Tichy.
- Photographs depicting activities of American, British, German and Italian armed forces in Europe and North Africa (Envelope N-AQ)
- Photographs taken by the U.S. Navy depicting ships and activities of the U.S. Navy, mostly in the Pacific Theater (Envelope AR)
- Photographs of British naval operations and of an inspection of naval forces by King George VI (Envelope AS)
- Photographs of Prime Minister Winston Churchill with high U.S. and British naval officers and other officials, 1942 July (Envelope AT)
- Photographs of U.S. armed forces in Great Britain (Envelope AU-AW)
- Photographs of U.S. armed forces in the Pacific (Envelope AX)
- Photographs of the U.S. Navy Public Relations Officers' Conference, Washington, D.C., 1943 April 26-28 (Envelope AY)
- Photographs of U.S. and British armed forces (Envelope AZ)
- Aerial photographs of military facilities at Londonerry, Northern Ireland (Envelope BA)
- 34 post cards of German SS troops on the Russian front (Envelope BB)
- 125 prints of German seamen, submarines and other ships, and of naval engagements (Envelope BC-BD)
  Captions in German.
- 43 prints of German troops in France, Norway and elsewhere on the Western Front (Envelope BE)
- 6 prints of German troops in North Africa (Envelope BF)
- 9 prints of German troops in the Balkans (Envelope BG)
- 6 prints of Benito Mussolini and of German troops who rescued him from captivity, 1943 (Envelope BH)
  Captions in German and French.
- 21 prints of war damage, political activity and social conditions in Vichy France and in German-occupied France (Envelope BI)
  Captions in French.
- 93 prints of street scenes, buildings and war damage in Berlin (Envelope BJ-BK)
- 12 prints of U.S. Army Air Corps airplanes (Envelope BL)
- 12 prints of U.S. Navy airplanes (Envelope BM)
- 123 prints of German troops in Paris, 1940 Summer (Envelope BN-BO)
- 22 prints of Vichy youth organizations and miscellaneous scenes from Vichy France and German-occupied France (Envelope BP)
- 49 prints of the bodies of victims of German concentration camps at Buchenwald and elsewhere (Envelope BQ)
- 32 prints of American troops entering Liege, Belgium (Envelope BR)
- 39 prints of war damage in Liege and other Belgian cities (Envelope BS)
- 10 prints of President Harry S. Truman in Brussels and Antwerp, Belgium, en route to the Potsdam conference, 1945 July (Envelope BT)
- 22 prints of the entry of Allied troops into Antwerp, Belgium, 1944 September (Envelope BU)
- 4 post cards of the entry of Allied troops into Tournai, Belgium, 1944 September (Envelope BV)
- 16 prints of Tournai, Belgium, including scenes of war damage, 1940 May (Envelope BW)
- 12 prints of war damage caused by V-1 and V-2 rockets in Antwerp, Belgium; map showing location of rocket attacks in Antwerp (Envelope BX)
- 29 prints of U.S. armored amphibious personnel carriers in action, mainly in the Pacific Theater (Envelope BY)
- 20 prints of posters and street scenes in German-occupied France (Envelope BZ)
- 12 drawings of Allied troops in Belgium, 1944-1945 (Envelope mCA)
- 15 prints of unidentified ships, zeppelins, and barrage balloons (Envelope CB)
- Graves of American soldiers in Great Britain (3 pages from photograph album); 72 prints of miscellaneous scenes and groups of people (possibly in Great Britain) (Envelope CC)
- 2 prints of Admiral Harold Stark with others; 1 print of Admiral Stark, Winston Churchill, and others; 2 prints of Winston Churchill, Admiral Stark, Harry Hopkins and others (Envelope CD)
- 15 prints of unidentified people and scenes (Envelope CE)
- 28 prints of Japan and Pacific Islands (Envelope CF)
- 13 prints of Japan and Pacific Islands; 12 prints of World War II aircraft; 1 print of Lt. Gen. Tomoyuki Yamashita; 1 print of Gen. Dwight D. Eisenhower and Gen. Douglas MacArthur; 1 print of Gen. Douglas MacArthur, Lt. Gen. Jonathan Wainwright and Lt. Gen. A.E. Percival; 10 miscellaneous prints (Envelope CG)
- 13 prints of Japan; 4 postcards of Japan; 1 print of Kunming, China; 1 print of Hawaii (Envelope CH)
- 34 prints of scenes in Europe (Envelope CI)
- 34 prints of scenes in Europe (Envelope CJ)
- 18 prints of scenes in Europe; 6 prints of U.S. Army, University Study Center, Florence, Italy; 1 print of Secretary of War, Henry L. Stimson (July 4, 1944); 1 print of General Dwight D. Eisenhower (1944); 1 print of Pierre Laval, Benito Mussolini, and others (1944) (Envelope CK)
- 1 print of Gen. Geo. C. Marshall, Gen. Henry H. Arnold, Adm. Ernest J. King; 1 print of Harry S. Truman's headquarters, Potsdam, Germany (1945); 3 prints of Winston Churchill, Joseph Stalin, Harry S. Truman in Potsdam (1945); 3 prints of Harry S. Truman, Joseph Stalin, Clement Attlee and staff in Potsdam (1945); 1 print of Harry S. Truman, Joseph Stalin, James F. Byrnes, Vyacheslav Molotov, Adm. William Dr. Leahy in Potsdam (1945); 1 print of Franklin D. Roosevelt, Winston Churchill, and President Innonu of Turkey in Cairo, Egypt (1943); 1 print of W.L. Mackenzie King, Earl of Athlone and Princess Alice, wife of the Earl of Athlone; Pres. Franklin D. Roosevelt and Winston Churchill in Quebec, Canada (1943); 1 unidentified print, 1943-1945 (Envelope CL)
- 115 prints designated "Specimen of British War Literature," 1 print of Charles de Gaulle and others, 1 print of Winston Churchill and others (Envelope CM)
- 72 prints designated "Specimen of British War Literature;" 1 print of Omar Bradley, George Patton, and Dwight D. Eisenhower; 1 print of Dwight D. Eisenhower and others; 1 print of Nicholas Horthy, Prince Regent of Hungary with U.S. Maj. Gen. John E. Dahl; 1 print of Gen. George C. Marshall; 4 miscellaneous prints of war in the European Theatre (Envelope CN)
- 2 prints of German soldiers (Envelope mCO)
- 75 prints of German and Japanese troops, 1944 (Envelope CP)
- 8 prints of forced labor in Norway, Poland, and elsewhere in German-occupied Europe (Envelope CQ)
- 15 prints of starvation, food lines, and German regulations relating to food in Belgium, Norway, Poland, and Greece (Envelope CR)
- 73 prints of resistance activities in German-occupied Norway, Belgium, France, Poland, Yugoslavia, and Greece, including scenes of guerilla activity, sabotage, underground presses, and passive resistance (Envelope CS)
- 8 prints of German executions and concentration camps in Norway, Belgium, France, Poland, and Yugoslavia (Envelope CT)
- 11 prints of persecution of Jews in Poland (Envelope CU)
- 12 prints of the German invasions of Poland and Norway, and of German proclamations (Envelope CV)
- 9 prints of miscellaneous scenes of the German occupation of Belgium and Poland (Envelope CW)
- 8 prints of resistance activity in German-occupied Norway, Poland, and Yugoslavia, including scenes of guerilla activity and passive resistance (Envelope mCX)
- 13 prints and 3 cartoons of conditions in German-occupied Norway, France, and Yugoslavia, including scenes of German executions, forced labor, and looting (Envelope mCY)
- 2 mounted prints of German troops arresting civilians in German-occupied Europe (Envelope mCZ)
- 1 mounted print of a child in German-occupied Europe (Envelope mDA)
- 5 prints, 5 charts and 1 cartoon from German-occupied Europe, depicting atrocities, food shortages, forced labor, and sabotage (Envelope mDB)
- 21 prints of refugees and resistance activities in German-occupied Europe and of an exhibit in the U.S. on resistance movements attended by Eleanor Roosevelt (Envelope DC)
- 14 prints of a wartime exhibit in the U.S. on resistance movements in Europe (Envelope mDD)
- 121 prints of refugees, executions, and resistance activities in Poland (Envelope DE)
- 83 prints of refugees, atrocities, and resistance activities in Greece and of Greek sailors in exile (Envelope DF)
- 5 drawings by children in France supporting French resistance activities (Envelope DG)
- 31 prints of French refugees, of resistance activities in Corsica and elsewhere in France, and of the scuttling of the French fleet at Toulon (Envelope DH)
- 11 prints of executions and resistance activities in Czechoslovakia (Envelope DI)
- 18 prints of resistance activities in Belgium and of martyred Belgian resistance members (Envelope DJ)
- 13 drawings of resistance activities in the Netherlands (Envelope DK)
- 11 prints of war shortages and resistance activities in Norway (Envelope DL)
- 5 prints of resistance activities in Norway (Envelope mDM)
- 11 prints of executions and resistance activities in Yugoslavia (Envelope DN)
- 23 prints of executions and resistance activities in Yugoslavia (Envelope mDO)
- 73 French post cards, depicting Free French, British, and other Allied military, naval, and aerial forces (Envelope DP)
- 40 German post cards, depicting Waffen-SS troops on the Eastern Front (Envelope DQ)
- 77 U.S. Army Signal Corps prints depicting scenes at the Nuremberg trials, disposal of German poison gas weapons by American occupation forces, and American troops in Europe at the end of the war, 1945-1947 (Envelope DR)
- 27 color slides of Axis and Allied propaganda posters (Envelope DS)
- 64 prints depicting Belgian underground resistance fighters in German-occupied Belgium during World War II, and of Allied troops entering Brussels in September 1944 (Envelope DT)
- 28 prints depicting Polish émigré politicians, statesmen, military personnel, establishments and buildings, 1941-1945 (Envelope DU)
- 130 prints depicting scenes in Warsaw and other parts of Poland during World War II (Envelope DV-DZ)
- 138 photographs depicting various French Resistance units while under formation, during period of instruction, and in action (Envelope EA-EB)
  Some were taken after the liberation of France; they refer to German atrocities committed against members of the Resistance as well as against the civilian population, celebration of the liberation, and General De Gaulle's visit to former resistance centers.
- 521 prints in 2 albums detailing the service of an unidentified Luftwaffe bomber officer, including the Polish campaign, the Channel Coast, and the Russian Campaign, 1939-1943 (Album fEC)
  Includes close-ups of aircraft; general views of Luftwaffe airfields and quarters; war damage in Poland, France, and Russia; and various personal family shots.
- 131 prints depicting social conditions and activities of German Nazi party officials during World War II, with emphasis on Gauleiter Fritz Waechtler of Bavaria (Envelope ED)
- 265 prints depicting war damage in Berlin at the end of World War II (Envelope EE-EJ)
- Photographs (1 booklet and loose prints) of the city of Braunschweig in central West Germany before and after destruction during World War II (Envelope EK)
  Includes a map.
- 1 album of prints depicting the funeral of R. Heydrich (1904-1942), Reich Protector for Bohemia and Moravia (Album fEL)
- 56 prints depicting conditions at the Breendonck concentration camp in Antwerp, Belgium, during World War II (Envelope EM)
- 7 prints depicting conditions at the Buchenwald concentration camp in Germany, circa 1945-1946 (Envelope EN)
- 90 prints taken by a Hungarian soldier in a Hungarian unit of the German Army during the German invasion of Russia, 1942 (Envelope EO)
- 4 prints depicting General Tomobum (Tomoyuki) Yamashita upon his arrival in Manila for his trial as a war criminal, 1945 October (Envelope EP)
- 53 prints depicting the Philippines during and following the Allied invasion, including 3 prints of general MacArthur and 1 print of the surrender proceedings on Luzon, 1944-1945 (Envelope EQ)
- 12 prints depicting war damage to various buildings in Manila, Philippines, 1944 (Envelope ER)
- 117 prints depicting areas and events before, during and following the battle of Okinawa, 1944-1945 (Envelope ES)
  Includes two maps depicting Japanese mine fields, roadblocks, and other military installations in December 1944 and March 1945.
- 4 prints depicting the surrender ceremony on the U.S.S. Missouri in Tokyo Bay, 1945 September 2 (Envelope ET)
- 5 prints depicting activities in the China-Burma-India Theater, 1944-1945 (Envelope Eu)
- 16 prints depicting V-E Day in Paris, 1945 May 8 (Envelope EW)
- 41 prints depicting various aspects of the surrender of the German Navy under the supervision of the Allied Control Commission, in Flensburg, 1945 (Envelope EX)
- 52 prints depicting war damage in Coblenz, Frankfurt-am-Main, Goettingen, Hamburg, Hanover, Hochst, Kiel, Mainz, Neumuenster, Wesel, and Wiesbaden, 1945 (Envelope EY)
- 211 prints depicting war damage in Berlin, 1945 (Envelope EZ-FB)
- 2 autographed prints of Admiral Chester W. Nimitz at the signing of the Japanese surrender on board the U.S.S. Missouri and one photostatic copy of the signature sheet of the surrender document autographed by Admiral Nimitz, 1945 September 2 (Envelope mFC)
- 5 prints depicting war damage in Nuremberg, Germany (Envelope FD)
- 24 prints depicting the visit of Eleanor Roosevelt to Great Britain, 1942 November (Envelope FE)
- 5 prints with negatives showing various aspects of German fortifications on Normandy Beach (Envelope FF)
- 4 prints pertaining to the destruction of Caen, Normandy (Envelope FG)
- 1 print depicting U.S.S. Grayback coming into Midway for repairs (Envelope FH)
- 7 prints of the German surrender documents (Flensburg, Reims, and Berlin), 1945 (Envelope FI)
- 10 prints depicting the public hanging and burial of Benito Mussolini, 1945 (Envelope FJ)
- 24 prints depicting Poland during World War II and 4 negatives depicting Jews being rounded up in the Warsaw Ghetto (Envelope FK)
- 6 prints depicting Yugoslavia during World War II (Envelope FL)
- One album of prints, signed by Zhukov, depicting an exhibition in Leningrad for a dedication to Dwight D. Eisenhower during World War II (Album fFM)
- 17 prints depicting various aerial battles over Europe during World War II (Folder m*FN)
- 64 prints depicting Iron Cross recipients, and German air, ground and naval activities, including Bulgaria, Greece, France, and the Soviet Union (Envelope FO)
  Also includes Jakob Stalin.
- 24 prints depicting German-Italian relations; the Romanian State visit to Berlin in 1940; and German, Italian, French, and English leaders including Hitler, Goering, Seyss-Inquart, Mussolini, Italian Foreign Minister Count Galenzzo Ciano, Philippe Pétain, and Winston Churchill (Envelope FP)
  Also included are 3 prints of the German Western front (Siegfried Line).
- 9 prints depicting the German domestic front and German war production including physical fitness for prospective troops (Envelope FQ)
- 7 prints depicting a variety of scenes including the British Free Masonry in Berlin, the flight of Soviet citizens, the destruction of Soviet cities, the training or Allied troops, and the Japanese occupation of Shanghai (Envelope FR)
- 5 prints depicting England in German character, illustrated in cartoon style; 1 print of the Italian Air Force (Envelope FS)
- 42 prints depicting mainly scenes of the Sino-Japanese War and of daily life in Japan, especially war preparations by the Japanese Army and population at large, 1937-1938 (Envelope FT)
  Issued for the most part by the Japan Press Illustration Service.
- 3 prints depicting ceremonies of surrender of the German Army at Reims and Cordon in France and in Berlin; 1 print depicting Gen. Sir Bernard L. Montgomery; 1 print depicting Lt. Gen. Sir Edmond Schreiber; 1 print depicting Gen. Charles de Gaulle; 1 print depicting Gen. George C. Marshall talking to American soldiers in Germany, accompanied by Major General Raymond O. Barton and Major General Leonard T. Gerow; and 1 print depicting American soldiers inspecting a German tank destroyed by the advancing Third U.S. Army in Eastern France, 1944-1945 (Envelope FU)
- 23 prints depicting Allied prisoners of war in Germany and Italian prisoners of war in Egypt engaged in various sports and board games facilitated by the War Prisoners' Aid Committee of the YMCA, and employees of the Committee packing items at the Geneva Office in Switzerland (Envelope FV)
- 20 prints of the ceremonial signing of the Japanese surrender on the U.S.S. Missouri, 1945 September 2 (Envelope FW)
- 4 prints of Adolf Hitler and Benito Mussolini attending a military review; and 1 print of Italian Partisans in Turin, 1945, undated (Envelope FX)
- 1 mounted print depicting the raising of the Soviet flag over the Reichstag in Germany with caption in Russian, 1945 May 2 (Envelope mFY)
- 15 prints of scenes of naval warfare in the Atlantic Ocean and of American naval construction, 1941-1942 (Envelope FZ)
- Prints of the Japanese surrender at the end of World War II, 1942, 1945 (Box 1)
  Includes an autographed print of Gen. Douglas MacArthur and a print of an American bomber in India (1942).
- Photographs of Todd-California Shipbuilding Corporation, 1941 (Box 2)
  Contains photographs of the visit of Viscount Halifax and other scenes of the Todd-California Shipbuilding Corporation from preconstruction to 1941.
- Declassified U.S. government records, 1942-1945
  - 2018 release of declassified records, 1942-1945 (Reading room workstation)